本剧改编自圣经  这些故事曾改变世界
本剧将始终保持《圣经》真谛
《圣经》前情提要
Previously on The Bible.
起初  天主创造天地
In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth.
天主说  有光
And God said, "Let there be light."
亚当和厄娃违背天主的旨意  偷食禁果
Adam and Eve disobeyed God and ate the forbidden fruit.
其后  加音杀了亚伯尔
Since then, since Cain killed Abel,
天主目睹了人类内心深处太多的恶念
God has seen too much evil in human hearts.
天主预先警告我  要我造一座方舟
God warned me. He told me to build a boat.
天主向我说话
God has spoken to me.
他将指引我们去新的家园
He will lead us to a new home.
他保证我的后裔会多如繁星
He has promised descendents as numerous as the stars.
-你是谁  -我是梅瑟
- Who are you? - My name is Moses.
天主派遣我回来  使你们得自由
God has sent me to set you free.
上主将我们从埃及解救出来
The Lord brought us out from Egypt.
他也承诺将赐予我们这片土地
He promised us this land!
很快  它就会是我们的了
Soon it will be ours!
耶路撒冷  我们的新家园
Jerusalem, our new home.
达味  你在人间建立了天主的国度
David, you have forged God's nation on earth.
天主已经抛弃你了
God has forsaken you.
他想找一个顺服他心意的人
He wants a man after his own heart.
我坚信您的儿子必是应许为王的那一位
I believe your son is the promised king of his people.
他叫什么名字
What is his name?
耶稣
Jesus.
他的名字是耶稣
His name is Jesus.
即将到来的那一位  大过我
There is one to come, greater than me,
我不过是旷野中的声音 准备道路
I am just the voice in the wilderness, preparing the way for the...
迎接上主的到来
Lord.
-过些日子我们就去耶路撒冷  -那太危险了
- Soon we go to Jerusalem. - It's too dangerous.
这个来自加里肋亚的扰乱者是个麻烦
This agitator from Galilee, he's trouble.
-他要去哪里  -他朝圣殿去了 大司祭
- Where is he headed? - Towards the temple, High Priest.
天主会将他的忿怒降在所有人身上
God will bring his wrath down upon all of us,
谁知道比拉多会做什么
and who knows what Pilate will do?
大人  有个犹太人在圣殿里惹麻烦
Sir, a Jew has been causing trouble in the temple.
你们不能事奉天主而又事奉钱财
You cannot serve God and money.
倘若动乱在明日再次发生
If the disturbances that took place today are repeated tomorrow,
我会立即关闭圣殿
I will shut the temple immediately.
你们拆毁这座圣殿 三天之内 我要把它重建起来
Destroy this temple and I will build it again in three days.
他威胁说要拆毁圣殿
He has threatened to destroy the temple.
我们得除掉此人  否则罗马人将摧毁一切
We remove this man, or the Romans destroy everything.
-处决？  -没错
- Execute? - Yes.
一个乡下人的性命
The life of one peasant...
换取天主之国的未来
for the future of God's nation.
我永不离弃你
I will not fall away.
伯多禄  你要三次不认我
Peter, you will deny me three times.
-不  -快跑啊  耶稣
- No! - Run, Jesus!
快跑
Run!
告诉盖法我们抓到耶稣了
Tell Caiaphas we have Jesus.
-耶稣被捕了  -被捕了
- Jesus has been arrested. - Arrested?
-你是不是天主子  -我是
- Are you the Son of God? - I am.
亵渎者
Blasphemer!
圣经
耶路撒冷
逾越节前12个小时
感谢YYETS字幕组
原始翻译时间轴及制作
天主教长沙青年团体重制
本字幕采用天主教思高译本
仅供福传学习
禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!
您的逾越节长袍  大司祭
Your Passover robes, High Priest.
当判死刑  但不能用石头打死
The sentence is death, but it cannot be by stoning.
亵渎天主的惩罚自该如此
It's the penalty for blasphemy.
那么多民众
The crowds-
他有数以万计的支持者
He has thousands of supporters.
事态很容易失控  我不敢冒这个险
It could be disastrous. I dare not risk it.
比拉多
Pilate.
让比拉多来处决  他有权威
Pilate can do it. He has the authority.
罗马有什么理由处决耶稣
Why would the Romans execute Jesus?
比拉多奉命维持犹太地区的和平
Pilate is charged with keeping peace in Judaea.
这是我们的共同利益
It's in our common interest.
我得让他明白这一点
I must make him see that.
让人们知道  那匝肋人耶稣
Let it be known, Jesus of Nazareth has been tried
已经过长老最高法院的审理
by the supreme court of elders,
他已经有亵渎上主
and he has been found guilty of blasphemy...
并威胁损毁圣殿的罪
and of threatening to destroy the temple.
你们找他做什么
What do you want with him?
只是谈谈
Just to talk.
判决...
The sentence...
死刑
is death.
你  拿回你们的臭钱吧
You! Take back your money!
你
You.
我见过你  你认识他
I've seen you before. You know him.
不
No.
我不认识他
I don't know him.
你管他叫辣彼来着
You called him Rabbi.
他跟我没关系
He has nothing to do with me.
你认识他  我见过你俩在一起
You know him, I've seen you with him.
我不认识他
I don't know him.
伯多禄
Peter,
你要三次不认我
you will deny me three times.
不要怕
Don't be afraid.
带他去比拉多那里
Take him to Pilate.
我的妻子呢  已经很晚了
Where's my wife? It's late.
主人  请快来
Please master, come quickly!
克劳狄雅  怎么了
Claudia, what?
我
I-
我在梦里
I saw a man...
见到一个人
in a dream.
被殴打...
A man being beaten...
然后被杀
and killed.
他是无辜的
An innocent man!
是圣人
A holy man.
是好人
A good man.
-扶夫人上床  -不
- Help your lady back to bed. - No.
杀他的人  是你
It was you who killed him.
你们中有一位
One of you here...
将出卖我
will betray me.
大人  盖法大司祭和长老们求见
Sir, the High Priest Caiaphas and the elders are here to see you.
总督大人  早上好
Prefect, good morning.
总督大人  我们需要你的帮助
Prefect, we need your help.
我们已将一个危险犯人缉拿归案
We have convicted a dangerous criminal.
他必须被判死刑
His sentence must be death.
是么 那就处决他
So? Execute him.
我们不能
We cannot.
逾越节近了
This close to Passover,
鲜血会让我们不圣洁
it would make us impure.
那就逾越节过后再处决
So do it after Passover.
他是一个迫近的威胁
He is an immediate threat...
不光是对我们  你们也不例外
not only to us, but to you.
现在局势紧张
This is a tense time...
当我的族人在为
when my people celebrate...
摆脱过去压迫者的奴役而欢庆之时
their deliverance from past oppressors.
他自称是我们的王
He claims to be our king...
而且正煽动群众叛乱
and is whipping up the crowds into a rebellion,
这场叛乱可能把耶路撒冷搞得四分五裂
a rebellion that could tear Jerusalem apart.
凯撒会不高兴的
Caesar would not be pleased.
-他的名字  -那匝肋人耶稣
- His name. - Jesus of Nazareth.
你最好别浪费我时间
You better not be wasting my time.
我去会会那个犯人
I'll see the prisoner.
你  请停下
You! Stop, please.
请等等  求你了
Please wait! Please!
你认识耶稣  你和他说过话
You know Jesus. You spoke to him.
求你了  我的儿子在哪儿
Please, where's my son?
-他走了  -走了  去哪了
- He's gone.  - Gone? Where?
-别走  -求您了
- No. - Please.
-他被罗马人抓走了  -罗马人
- The Romans have him.  - The Romans?
他从未说过任何反对罗马的言论
He's never said anything against Rome.
那么
So,
告诉我你是谁
tell me who you are.
你是犹太的君王吗
Are you the king of the Jews?
这话是你由自己说的
Are you asking,
或是别人论我而对你说的
or is it a question coming from others?
你是君王吗
Are you a king?
你的民族和司祭长把你交付给我
That's what your own people and chief priest...
说你自称为王
tell me you claim to be.
我的国
My kingdom...
不属于这世界
is not of this world.
假使我的国属于这世界
If it were,
我的臣民早已反抗了 使我不至于被交给犹太人
my servants would fight my arrest.
但是我的国不是这世界的
My kingdom is from another place.
那么  你就是君王了
You are a king then.
你说的是 我是君王
You say that I am a king.
我为此而生
I have been born...
我也为此而来到这世界上
and come into the world...
为给真理作证
to testify to the truth.
凡属于真理的
Everyone on the side of truth...
必听从我的声音
listens to me.
真理
Truth?
什么是真理
What is truth?
那就是他
That's him.
我在梦中看到的人  就是他
The man I saw in the dream. That's him!
他们想把他钉十字架
They want him crucified.
你不能这么做
You can't.
他们说他会引发叛乱
They say he could start a revolution.
你不要这么做
You mustn't!
如果我不这么做
If I don't,
盖法会将任何叛乱归咎于我
Caiaphas will blame any rebellion on me,
凯撒会认为那是我的失职
Caesar will see it as my failure.
他已经警告过我一次
He has warned me once.
不会再给我第二次机会了
He is not going to warn me again.
到时我就完了
I'll be finished.
我们就都完了
We'll be finished.
这个人的罪至多不过受人迷惑
He's guilty of nothing more than being deluded.
他触犯了法律
He has broken the law.
你们的法律  不是凯撒的
Your law, not Caesar's.
放他出来  教他点礼数
Get him out and teach him some respect.
打四十鞭
Forty lashes.
四十鞭
Forty lashes?
仅此而已吗
Nothing more?
总督
Prefect,
倘若你释放了一个
we cannot be held responsible...
触犯我们天主神圣法律的人
for what the people may do today...
那么如果那些信仰天主的民众
with their eyes on God...
今日不论做出何等举动
if you release a man...
都一概与我们无关
who has broken our sacred laws.
民众
The people?
凯撒颁布法令说
Caesar decrees...
在逾越节  我可以释放一名犯人
I can release a prisoner at Passover.
那就让民众决定我手中哪一名犯人
Let the people decide which of the prisoners I hold...
将被钉上十字架
will be crucified.
过来
Come on!
快走  跟上
Move your feet! Come on!
过来
Come on!
这儿  快跟上
Here! Quickly!
他们对他做了什么
What have they done to him?
他们要杀了他
They're going to kill him!
似乎一切都在他的预料之中
It's as if he knows this must happen.
这么说你是王
So you're a king.
每个王都需要一个冠冕
Every king needs a crown.
站起来
Get up!
放他们进来
Let them in.
-没错  -你  你  还有你
- Yes.  - You. You and you.
-你  -你
- You.  - You.
-没错  -你
- Yes.  - You.
在那儿等着
Wait there.
不  你不行  回去  回去
No, not you. Back. Back.
不  退后  你不行  回去
No! Step back! Not you. Back.
不要推搡
No pushing!
让我过去吧
Let me through!
回去  不行  不行
Back! No. No.
走开
Get away!
关上门
Close the gates!
玛利亚  玛利亚  走吧
Hey! Mary! Mary, move.
走吧  我们走
Move. Let's go.
今天  逾越节开始了
Today, Passover begins.
你们的君主  凯撒奥古斯都
And your emperor, Tiberius Caesar,
给你们一个仁慈的恩典
makes you a gesture of good will-
按你们的选择
the release of a prisoner-
释放一个囚犯
chosen by you.
选择权在你们
I give you a choice.
巴辣巴
Barabbas-
一个危险的强盗
a dangerous agitator,
和臭名昭著的杀人犯
a common murderer.
还是这个传道者
Or this preacher,
他自称是你们的君王
who claims to be your king.
他才不是我们的王
He is not our king!
凯撒才是我们的王
We have no king but Caesar.
你们必须做出选择
You must decide.
我们选巴辣巴
We choose Barabbas.
-释放巴辣巴  -巴辣巴
- Free Barabbas. - Barabbas.
他是我们的兄弟
He's one of us.
释放巴辣巴给我们
Give us Barabbas!
巴辣巴  巴辣巴
Barabbas! Barabbas!
耶稣  耶稣
Jesus! Jesus!
巴辣巴  巴辣巴
Barabbas! Barabbas!
你们选择杀人犯
You choose a murderer?
释放巴辣巴给我们
Give us Barabbas!
执行吧
Do it!
跟我走
Let's go.
那这先知呢
And the prophet?
这等的亵渎者怎么会是我们的王呢
How could this blasphemer be our king?
他才不是我们的王
He's not our king.
把他钉十字架
Crucify him!
处死他
Kill him!
把他钉十字架
Crucify him!
-赦免他  -救救他
- Spare him! - Save him!
-处死他  -把他钉十字架
- Kill him! - Crucify him!
了结他的痛苦吧
Put him out of his misery!
-把他钉十字架  -把他钉十字架
- Crucify him! - Crucify him!
钉十字架
Crucify him!
你们怎能处决这人  却赦免杀人犯呢
How can you condemn this man and spare a murderer?
把他钉十字架
Crucify him!
亵渎者
Blasphemer!
好吧
Very well.
把他钉十字架
Crucify him!
处死他
Let him die!
不要
No!
你  退后
You! Get back!
请释放他吧
Release him!
快走
Move!
罗马渣滓
Roman scum!
他们怎能如此对他
How can they treat him like this?
若望  我要去见他
John, I need to see him.
我要去见我的儿子
I need to see my son.
退后
Get back!
让他们退后
Move them back!
贺三纳  贺三纳  贺三纳
Hosanna! Hosanna! Hosanna!
后边去
Get back there!
罗马刽子手
Roman murderers!
不  耶稣  来人帮帮他
No! Jesus! Somebody help him!
请怜悯他
Show him mercy!
不要
No!
退后  别过来
Get back! Stay back!
我的孩子
My son.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
在天主  万事皆有可能
Everything is possible with God.
快走
Move forward!
耶稣  耶稣
Jesus! Jesus!
求你们了  她是他母亲
Please, she's his mother!
退后  再退
Get back! Further back!
退后
Get back!
来人帮帮他
Somebody help him!
求你们了
Please!
你
You!
帮他背十字架
Help him carry the cross.
快走
Move!
我的上主
My Lord.
总督大人  他十字架上的牌子要怎么写
What will the sign on his cross say, Prefect?
用希伯来  罗马  希腊三样文字写
Put in Aramaic, Latin and Greek
" 那匝肋人耶稣 犹太人的君王 "
"Jesus of Nazareth, the king of the Jews."
他从不是我们的王
He was never our king.
该写他自己说
It must read, "This man said...
"我是犹太人的君王"
'I am the king of the Jews."'
我写了 就写了  犹太人的君王
It stays as I 've commanded. The king of the Jews.
一群懦夫
Cowards!
滚开
Get away!
我的上主  祝福你
My Lord. Bless you.
谢谢
Thank you.
快点  动起来
Come on! Move!
快走
Move it!
Move!
快点  说你呢  赶上
Come on! Hey, come on!
快点  快走
Faster! Move!
你  走开  走开
You! Leave! Leave!
快走
Move!
来吧  王
Come on, king.
快点
Come on!
来吧  开始吧
Come on. Come on!
把他放到十字架上
Get him up on the cross!
快点
Come on!
不准靠近了
No further.
绑紧绳子
Secure the ropes.
纳匝肋人耶稣 犹太人的君王 [三语书写]
你将为此事悔恨终生
You'll live to regret this.
我们又不是第一次杀犹太人了
Hardly the first Jew we've killed.
他不一样
He was different.
他是天主选中的人
He was chosen by the gods.
他认为他是
He thought he was.
一周之内就没人记得他是谁了
He'll be forgotten in a week.
把他拉起来
Get him up there!
稳住
Steady!
我的儿啊
My son.
犹太人的君王
King of the Jews!
在上面能看到圣殿吗
Can you see the temple from there?
滚开
Leave him.
父啊
Father!
宽赦他们吧
Forgive them,
因为他们不知道他们做的是什么
for they know not what they do.
你先来
You first.
真不走运
Bad luck.
你不是默西亚吗
Aren't you the Messiah?
救救你自己和我们吧
Why don't you save yourself and us?
我们所受的 正配我们所行的
Our punishment is just,
但是 这个人...
but this man...
从未做过什么坏事
has done nothing wrong.
耶稣 当你来为王时  请你纪念我
Remember me when you come into your kingdom.
我实在告诉你
Truly I say to you,
今天
today,
你就要与我一同在乐园里
you will be with me in paradise.
母亲
Mother,
看 你的儿子
this is your son.
若望
John,
看 你的母亲
this is your mother.
我的天主
My God.
你为什么舍弃了我
Why have you forsaken me?
我渴
I thirst.
完成了
It's finished.
父啊
Father,
我把我的灵魂
into your hands...
交托在你手中
I commit my spirit.
-克劳狄雅  -这是一个预兆
- Claudia!  - This is an omen.
把尸体搬走
Take the body away.
等等
Wait!
这是般雀·比拉多的命令
I have an order from Pontius Pilate.
尸体是我们的
This body is ours.
给他们
Give it to them.
三天后
那时你在哪
Where were you?
你应该是他的磐石
You were supposed to be his rock.
我辜负了他
I failed him.
如今也无法请求他的原谅
Now I can't ask him to forgive me.
如果有任何需要就回来
Come back if you need anything.
我会的
I will.
祝你回加里肋亚一路平安
Have a safe journey back to Galilee.
愿上主祝福你
Bless you.
你在找谁
Who are you looking for?
若是你把他移了去  请告诉我他在哪里
If you've taken him, tell me where he is.
玛利亚
Mary.
老师
Teacher?
去告诉我们的弟兄们
Go and tell our brothers...
我回来了
I am here.
《圣经》下集预告
Next time on The Bible.
墓穴是开着的  我看见他了
The tomb is open. I saw him!
伯多禄
Peter?
他没死  他回来了
He hasn't gone. He's back.
因为你看见了我
Because you see me,
才相信我
you believe.
不  这不是真的
No, this isn't real.
多默  不要再疑虑
Thomas, stop doubting.
真的是你
It is you.
当圣神降临在你们身上
When the holy spirit comes to you,
你们将佩戴上自高天而来的能力
you will receive power.
我奉耶稣基督之名  叫你起来行走
In the name of Jesus Christ, rise up and walk.
耶稣做到了
Jesus did this!
他们又在喊那个低贱之人的名字了
They're shouting that wretched man's name again!
如果你们再妖言惑众
You will be silent,
我就让你们再也出不了声
or you will be silenced.
亵渎者
Blasphemer!
我们不怕死
We are not afraid of death.
塔尔索的扫禄
Paul of Tarsus.
我能为你除掉这个渣滓
I could flush this scum out for you.
告诉你的朋友
Tell all your friends
我  塔尔索的扫禄
that I, Paul of Tarsus,
必找到你
will find you!
你是谁
Who are you?
告诉我你是谁
Tell me who you are!
宽恕我  是我得罪了天主
Forgive me. I've wronged God.
所有人皆可进此门
The door is open to everyone.
你必须和我们走一趟
You must come with us.
我们于苦难中欢欣
We rejoice in our suffering.
雅各伯
James!
不
No!
不再有死亡
There will be no more death...
也不再有悲哀
or mourning...
哭号
or crying...
疼痛
or pain.
总有东西要留传下去
Something must survive.
如果我死了
If not me,
至少让我的话留传下去
then my words at least.
我必快来
I am coming soon.
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!